The Life of Muhammadﷺ, The Madinan Period, Volume 1
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki,
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝
بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته
Rasool Allah ﷺ held a sword in his hand,
and he asked the Sahabah(صحابه), who will take this sword from me.
So, the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم volunteered.
But then Rasool Allah ﷺ said,
Who will take this sword along with its rights.
So, this sword you don't just take it.
I'm not just giving it to you, but this sword has some rights.
So, the Sahabah(صحابه) asked Rasool Allah ﷺ; What are the rights of this sword.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said; For you to strike the enemy with it, until it bends.
So, now the Sahabah(صحابه) were giving it a second thought,
I mean, taking a sword until you bend it.
But Abu Dujana رضي الله عنه came forward and said, I will, O Rasool Allah ﷺ,
I'm going to take it,
I'm up for that challenge,  I'll hit the enemy with it, until I bend it,
I'm going to bend that piece of steel.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ gives it to him.
Ibn Is'haaq(إبن اسحاق) says,
When he took the sword from Rasool Allah ﷺ, he took out the red headband and put it on.
He then began strutting about between the two lines.
Abu Dujana(ابودجانه), when he would fight, he would put on a red headband.
That's the sign that he's going to war.
So, he pulls up that red headband puts it on,
and then he starts to march in front of the army with pride.
He's emanating this pride you can feel the strength in his walk,
strutting in front of the enemy.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
That is a way of walking that Allah dislikes, except in circumstances like this.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ does not like this way of walking,
but in this particular situation, Allah does like it.
A Muslim is not supposed to be arrogant, so that's why we walk with humbleness,
we walk with humbleness.
Rasool Allah ﷺ would walk with humbleness,
now we don't want this to be misunderstood as walking with weakness,
the humbleness is something and weakness is something else.
Rasool Allah ﷺ when he would walk,
you can see the strength in Rasool Allah ﷺ in the way he would walk.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) said;
As if he's coming down a hill.
So, it's like firmness in walking.
So, that's different than, we shouldn't think that
being humble is that you're walking with weakness.
But here Abu Dujana(ابو دجانه) is walking with pride, Khuayalaa(خُيَّلَآءْ),
and that's not something that Allah likes, but this is done in front of the enemy.
And that's why Allahعَزّوجَلّ likes in this particular situation.
Imam Ahmad(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ) said: And he did take it,
referring to the sword, that he did take it
and cleaved a path with it, through the middle of the Polytheists.
In the middle of the Mushrikeen(مشركين)
So, Abu Dujana(ابو دجانه) takes this sword, in order to bend it,
he wrecks havoc in the ranks of the enemy and splits up their ranks,
he cleaved the path with it, through the middle of Al-Mushrikeen(ألمشركين).
Abdullah Bin Zubair(عبدالله بن الزبير), he narrates to us a story of a scene that he witnessed on the day of Uhud(أحَد).
He said, Every man he met Abu Dujana(ابو دجانه) killed.
Among the Mushrikeen(مشركين) there was man, who executed every man he wounded.
Meaning this man he doesn't spare the life of anyone.
If he meets a Muslim, A Muslim is dead.
This man and Abu Dujana(دجانه) came ever closer to one another.
And I pray to Allah to bring them together.
And they did meet.
They exchanged a couple of blows,
the Mushrik(مشرك) then struck at Abu Dujana(ابو دجانه),
who fended off the blow with his shield
which trap the man sword,
then Abu Dujana(ابو دجانه) struck and killed him.
Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) narrates a similar story,
Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم) if it's talking about the same person it could be or it could be somebody else.
Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) said, I then saw one Mushrik(مشرك) heavily armored
was striking the Muslims hard and saying Come on, you sheep gathering for slaughter.
But then I saw one Muslim fully armored,
I mean he doesn't know this Muslim was, his armory was covering the face.
But then I saw one Muslim fully armored waiting for him,
and I went on over behind him and began comparing the Muslim with the Mushrik(مشرك).
So, Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) here saw these two men and he was sizing them up.
He says the latter was better in equipment and form,
meaning the Mushrik(مشرك) was bigger and stronger and he also had better equipment,
so you would expect that the Mushrik(مشرك) would win.
I kept on waiting until they met.
The Muslim then struck the unbeliever a blow with his sword on his shoulder,
the sword came right down through, to his thigh.
So, he struck the Mushrik(مشرك) on the shoulder
and the sword went through tearing apart his torso
until it came out from under his thigh, cutting him into two.
Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) said: Then the Muslim uncovered his face and said,
What about that Ka'ab(كعب)? I'm Abu Dujana(ابودجانه).
So, Abu Dujana(ابودجانه) knew that Ka'ab(كعب) was watching and watching this match.
So, when the match was over, Abu Dujana(ابودجانه) uncovers his faces, and says,
What about that Ka'ab(كعب), I'm Abu Dujana(ابودجانه).
He was a proud man, and he has every right to be proud.
The Muslims were winning, and the enemy was fleeing the battle ground.
And the Sahabah(صحابه) said, We could see,
the women of Arabia used to put this jewelry on their feet.
So, they would say that we would see that jewelry on their feet
because they're tucking up their clothes to run away.
So, that's it. The enemy was showing the Muslims, their backs.
Bannu Abd-Ad-Daar(بنوعبدالدار) were the ones, who had the responsibility of holding the standard of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
And this was part of the Division of authorities that existed in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
one family would take care of feeding the pilgrims,
one family had the key to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه),
one family had the key to An-Nadwa(ألندوى), the sort of the Parliament of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
and one family, they held the banners of war.
So, this family was Bannu Abd-Ad-Daar(بنوعبدالدار),
they were the ones responsible for it on Badr(بدر) and they are also responsible for it, on Uhud(أحَد).
And I mean to show you the importance of the standard.
You know, because probably due to modern warfare, we don't really understand what's the significance of a banner.
That was the rallying point,
that was the indication to the soldier that we're still in the fight and my army is here.
Without the banner, the soldier is not going to fight anymore.
If the banner falls down, that means that we have lost the war,
and it's time for me to run away.
So to show the significance of this banner issue,
Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) told Bannu Abd-Ad-Daar(بنوعبدالدار);
You were incharge of our banner at the Battle of Badr(بدر).
And you saw what happened to us, men will only fight for their flags.
If once, they are lost, they withdraw,
either take care of our banner for us or give it over to us and we will relieve you of it.
So, this angered them and said we give over our banner to you.
You will learn tomorrow when we meet and in battle, how we will behave.
So, he charged them up.
And that was the response Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) wanted.
So they fought under their banner well.
I mean, Bannu Abd-Ad-Daar(بنوعبدالدار) they lost seven of their men one after the other.
One would hold the banner that he would be killed.
The second would come in line take it over, he would be killed,
third,
Seven of their men were killed carrying the banner
and then one of their slaves, his name is Sawaab(ثواب)
Abyssinian slave, he took hold of it and his arms were severed,
and he was still trying to hug the banner and then he would say, Aazart(أعذرْتْ)
Have I done my part and he couldn't pronounce the Za(ز), it was Azart( آعزرت)
but his Arabic wasn't perfect, so he said: Aazart(أعذرْتْ).
Anyway so after that the banner just fell down and they left it on the ground,
and that is when Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) started to flee the battle ground.
So, they were defeated, they lost
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ said,
وَلَقَدْ صَدَقَكُمُ اللَّهُ وَعْدَهُ إِذْ تَحُسُّونَهُمْ بِإِذْنِهِ ۖ
And Allah had certainly fulfilled His promise to you
when you were killing them by His permission.
So, even according to Qur'an, the Muslims have won the battle of Uhud(أحَد) initially.
But the tides were turning.
The archers, who were instructed by Rasool Allah ﷺ to remain on the hill not to move,
if you see us winning, Do not come down until I tell you,
if you see us losing and vultures picking off our bodies eating from our bodies,
Do not come down until I tell you, very explicit, clear, instructions from Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Now in the heat of battle when the emotions take over,
sometimes the mind is obscured.
So, what happened is, when the archers saw that the Muslims were now gathering booty, Al-Ghanaem(ألغنائم),
they wanted to go down and join.
But their Ameer(امير) Abdullah Bin Jubair(عبدالله بن جبير), he said,
Don't you remember the instructions of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
that we shouldn't come down, until he tells us so.
They said the battle is over and they left.
So, out of the 50 archers, 40 of them defected.
We're going to call this defection because that's what it is.
They have disobeyed the order of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and this is a serious thing in warfare, to disobey the commander.
Or not defected, we should call it, it was mutiny,
so they left their post.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was the head of the cavalry of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
He and Ikrimah Bin Abi Jahal(عكرمه بن ابي جهل).
When they detected the weak point, that was exposed
they immediately took advantage of that, and outflanked the Muslim army.
And because the Muslims were not expecting that, and they were taken by surprise.
It was a chaotic state for the Muslims,
and when the army of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) saw that they attacked from the other side,
so now the Muslims were sandwiched,
they were attacked from both sides from the front and from the rear.
And this disoriented the Muslim soldiers
because they are fighting now in both direction
and the ranks would became disorganized, they were not lined up properly as they should.
And that is when the Muslims were defeated.
And that is when they were being killed,
and they were falling one after the other.
It is said that only 12 men remained around Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Allahعزوجل says;
وَلَقَدْ صَدَقَكُمُ اللَّهُ وَعْدَهُ إِذْ تَحُسُّونَهُمْ بِإِذْنِهِ
حَتَّىٰ إِذَا فَشِلْتُمْ وَتَنَازَعْتُمْ فِي الْأَمْرِ وَعَصَيْتُمْ مِنْ بَعْدِ مَا أَرَاكُمْ مَا تُحِبُّونَ۝
مِنْكُمْ مَنْ يُرِيدُ الدُّنْيَا وَمِنْكُمْ مَنْ يُرِيدُ الْآخِرَةَ
ثُمَّ صَرَفَكُمْ عَنْهُمْ لِيَبْتَلِيَكُمْ وَلَقَدْ عَفَا عَنْكُمْۗ
وَاللَّهُ ذُو فَضْلٍ عَلَى الْمُؤْمِنِينَ۝
Allah has certainly fulfilled His promise to you,
when you were killing them by His permission, until the time when you lost courage
and fell to disputing about the order given by the prophet
and disobeyed after He had shown you
that which you love, I mean, victory.
After among you are some, who desire this world,
and among you are some who desire the Hereafter.
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) said, I didn't know
that there were some of us who loved and desire this world, until this Ayah(آية) was revealed.
So, Qur'an was exposing what was in the hearts
this is how Qur'an writes history,
it doesn't only take the outside, but it also takes the inner dimension of the soul.
Then Allah says, Then he turned you back from them defeated,
that He might test you.
And he has already forgiven you.
And Allah is the possessor of bounty for the believers.
So, Allah tested the believers with victory on Badr(بدر)
and He is now testing them with the defeat on Uhud(أحَد).
It's all test from Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Ibn Is'haqq(اِبْنِ اِسْحَاقْ) said, the Muslim ranks broke
and the enemy gained advantage over them.
It was the day of trial and testing, in which Allah honored someone with martyrdom.
At last the enemy broke through to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
he was hit with a rock
and fell on his side,
breaking his front teeth,
slashing his face and splitting his lips.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ himself was injured in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
In Al-Bukhari(البخاريْ) it says that Fatima(فاطمه) was the one, who was washing him,
and Ali(علي) poured the water from the shield.
So, Ali(علي) was pouring the water and
Fatima(فاطمه) was washing the wounds.
When Fatima(فاطمه) saw that the water was only increasing the blood flow
She took a piece of matting and she set fire to it and then attach it to the wound.
So, over here you have, it is ashes, and it's also hot
ashes are very dry and it would absorb the water from the wound and make it dry
and that would prevent the blood from flowing.
And It's also hot so it would probably disinfect the wound.
This is mentioned in Bukhari(بخاريْ), it says that the blood seized flowing
and his front tooth was broken that day his face was wounded
and his helmet was crushed onto his head.
It was Ibn Qamiyah(إبن قميه) who shot Rasool Allah ﷺ at the cheek
and it was Utba Bin Abi Waqas(عتبةبن ابي وقاص), who hit the lip and lower tooth of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Abdur Razzaq(عبدالرزاق) says,
The Messenger of Allah spoke a curse against Utba Bin Abi Waqas(عتبة بن ابي وقاص) saying;
O Allah may change not come to him.
So, that he does die as an unbeliever.
Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) commented
and no change did come over him so that he did die as an unbeliever bound for hellfire.
So, what was the reaction to this defeat,
Rasool Allah ﷺ as narrated by Anas Ibn Malik رضي الله عنه, he said,
While Rasool was wiping the blood off his face,
He said, How could any people prosper,
Who struck their prophet and broke his front teeth?
While he called people to Allah.
How could these people prosper?
How could they succeed?
When they do this to the Prophet who's calling them to Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed the Ayah(آية),
لَيْسَ لَكَ مِنَ الْأَمْرِ شَيْءٌ أَوْ يَتُوبَ عَلَيْهِمْ أَوْ يُعَذِّبَهُمْ فَإِنَّهُمْ ظَالِمُونَ۝
Not for you, O Muhammad(محمد) but for Allah is the decision
whether He should cut them down or forgive them or punish them.
For indeed they are wrongdoers.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ is saying, The fate of these people is not up to you
It's in the hands of Allahعَزّوجَلّ
It is up to Allahعَزّوجَلّ to cut them down, or to forgive them, or to punish them.
They deserve punishment but if Allahعَزّوجَلّ wants to forgive them, it is up to Him.
So, this shows you that even Rasool Allah ﷺ does not control the fate of humanity.
It's all in the hands of Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
Allahعَزّوجَلّ is the One, Who controls, who becomes Muslim and who doesn't
and who should be punished and who shouldn't be punished.
So, if this right wasn't given to Rasool Allah ﷺ
who are we to claim that right?
It's all in the hands of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Some of the Muslims, when they saw the defeat,
and when they heard the rumor that Rasool Allah ﷺ was killed
because this rumors spread like wildfire in the Muslim army that he was killed.
The origin of the rumor was that he was injured,
but you know, in such a state, things could get blown out of proportion.
So, the rumor that was going around was that Rasool Allah ﷺ was in fact killed.
So, how did they react to that?
Well, some of them said,
We'd better send an envoy to Abdullah Bin Obaeye(عبدالله بن ابيئ)
and have him get us a truce from Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان).
People! Muhammad(محمد) has been killed, go back home before they get to you and kill you.
Here we have some Muslims, who are defeated, the defeat reached to their hearts.
And under the pressure of the moment,
they thought that the best course of action was to go to Abdullah Bin Obaeye(عبدالله بن ابي), the Munafiq(منافق)
because he has good relations with Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) and to ask him to bring a truce.
And Ya'ani(يعني) Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله),
The Battle of Uhud(أحَد), itself may not repeat
but the reaction of the people can repeat in events that are similar.
So, sometimes you'd find that when Muslims are under pressure and
when they feel that they could be defeated in battle,
you can have some people who would now think well, why don't I go to the government's
and ask them to help me or why don't I go to the enemies of Allahعَزّوجَلّ and let's have a truce with them.
This is a sign of weakness.
But the Muslims, who had strong Eeman(ايمان) in their hearts, what was their reaction?
One of Al-Muhajiroon(المهاجرون) said that he passed by one of Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار)
a man, who was covered in his own blood,
He was soaked in his own blood and asked him.
Are you aware that Muhammad(محمد) has been killed.
The Ansaari(انصاري) responded if Muhammad(محمد) has been killed
then he must have fulfilled his mission, so fight on for your religion.
Let's die as he died fighting for Islam.
So, these are Muslims, who cannot be defeated in their hearts,
even if they're defeated on the battleground,
defeat will never get into their spirit.
They will always have commitment
and this is, what is called in Islam thabaat(ثبات) steadfast.
Never would such a Muslim try to negotiate with the enemy of Allahعَزّوجَلّ
or ask the Munafiqeen(منافقين), to appeal and intercede for them.
Fine, if Rasool Allah ﷺ was killed, we're gonna die like he was.
And this is the steadfastness that we should learn from the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
The Muslims had to retreat,
so Rasool Allah ﷺ was trying to organize that retreat,
but retreats could be catastrophic if they are not commanded well.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ wants to organize this retreat
and to protect themselves while they are retreating.
So, the enemy now was gaining the upper hand and was attacking in full force
and they were getting closer to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, Rasool Ullah asked,
He said, Whoever will repel them, will be my companion in paradise.
I mean, that's how difficult the situation was,
Rasool Ullah was promising paradise
to the one, who will succeed in stopping the attacks of the kuffar(كفار) that were reaching him.
So, one of Al-Ansaar(الانصار) volunteered
and he would fire his arrows at the enemy until he was killed.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ asks for a volunteer another time,
another Ansari(انصاري) comes up, he's also killed
and a third time, a third Ansaari(انصاري) would stand up
and then a fourth
and the fifth and every time they're killed,
so this in addition to the sacrifice of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار),
can also show you the disastrous effect this attack of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) was having,
it was a strong attack, until seven of Al-Ansaar(الانصار) died under Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Allah u Akbar(الله اكبر).
Seven bodies, laying under the feet of Rasool Allah ﷺ, to defend him.
And that's why they were called Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار)
and you're going to hear me repeat this again and again.
That's why they're called Ansaar(انصار)
they didn't receive this title, this honor of being Ansaar(انصار),
which is given to them in Qur'an and by Rasool Allah ﷺ,
they didn't get that out of nothing, they earned it.
You have seven young men, dead under the feet of Rasool Allah ﷺ defending him, giving their lives for him.
May Allah be pleased with them.
In Al-Bukhari(البخاريْ), Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) says,
I never heard the Prophet of Allah swear by both his parents to anyone
except Saad Ibn Malik(سعدابن مالك), or Saad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدابن ابي وقاص).
At Uhud(أحَد) I heard him say; Sa'ad(سعد) shoot
May my father and my mother be your ransom. Allah U Akbar(الله اكبر)
This Dua(دعا) for Saad Ibn Malik(سعدابن مالك)
Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying; May my father and mother be your ransom O Sa'ad(سعد).
That is how pleased Rasool Allah ﷺ was with the performance of Saad Ibn Abi Waqasرضي الله عنه.
And another hero next to Rasool Allah ﷺ, standing next to him and defending him, was Talha Bin Ubaidellah رضي الله عنه.
At the Battle of Uhud(أحَد) and this is narrated by Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك) in Musnad Imam Ahmad(مسند امام احمد)
He said that at the Battle of Uhud(أحَد),
Abu Talha(ابوطلحه) was shooting directly in front of Rasool Allah ﷺ, who was shielding himself behind him.
As he shot the Messenger of Allah would raise himself up to see where the arrows would strike.
At this Abu Talha(ابوطلحه) would say as he brought his chest up to its full height,
Let it be so, May my father and my mother be your ransom or messenger of Allah
no arrow will hit you, my chest will be in the way of yours.
لا اله الا الله
And he would also say I am sturdy O Messenger of Allah
direct me according to your needs and order me to do, whatever you want.
These were the companions of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Allah ﷺ retreated to the mountain of Uhud(أحَد) itself
in a crevice in the mountain, that's where he withdrew to.
climbing up the mountain was difficult for him.
So Talha(طلحه) had to carry him because Rasool Allah ﷺ was injured.
And when they climbed up the mountain, that is when the battle stopped
because Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) dared not to pursue the Muslims up the mountain.
And plus the cavalry cannot fight in such terrain.
So, it would have to be the foot soldiers and this was something the enemy wasn't ready or prepared to do.
So, now Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Muslims were up in the mountain of Uhud(أحَد).
And Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) approaches them, and he calls to them.
He said,
Is Muhammad(محمد) alive.
And he hears no answer.
He then asks, Is Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) alive?
No response.
Is Umar(عُمَر) alive.
So, Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) is now happy and he told his people that these men have been killed.
Now Umar Bin Khattab(عمر بن خطاب) couldn't stand hearing Abu Sufiyan(ابو سفيان) say that.
So he said,
The three men whom you mentioned are alive to upset you.
So, Abu Sufiyan(ابو سفيان) responded back, he said,
A battle for the Battle of Badr(بدر),
warfare goes in cycles,
meaning one day you win, one day we win.
And you will find some bodies mutilated
I did not order that, but it didn't bother me.
Raise up Hubal(حبل), Raise up Hubal(حبل) and he started chanting,
Raise up Hubal(حبل).
So Rasool Allah ﷺ said,
Aren't you gonna respond back.
They said, What should we say?
He said, Say
Allah is higher and more glorious
and this rhymes with what Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان), said,
He said,
أُعْلُوْا هُبَلْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ said,
اَلله اَعْلى وَ اَجَلْ
Allah is higher and more glorious.
Hubal(حبل) by the way is one of their idols.
He said,
لَنَا الْعُزَّى وَلَاعُزَّى لَكُمْ
We have Al-Uzza(عزى), another idol,
and you have no Uzza(عزى).
Rasool Allah ﷺ told them to respond by saying,
اَللهُ مَوْلَانَا وَلَامَوْلَى لَكُمْ
Allah is our master, and you have no master.
Allah describes the climbing of the Muslims up the mountain of Uhud(أحَد).
Allahعَزّوجَلّsays,
إِذْ تُصْعِدُونَ وَلَا تَلْوُونَ عَلَىٰ أَحَدٍ وَالرَّسُولُ يَدْعُوكُمْ فِي أُخْرَاكُمْ
وَالرَّسُولُ يَدْعُوكُمْ فِي أُخْرَاكُمْ فَأَثَابَكُمْ غَمًّا بِغَمٍّ لِكَيْلَا تَحْزَنُوا
لِكَيْلَا تَحْزَنُوا عَلَىٰ مَا فَاتَكُمْ وَلَا مَا أَصَابَكُمْ ۗ
وَاللَّهُ خَبِيرٌ بِمَا تَعْمَلُونَ۝
Remember when you fled and climb the mountain without looking aside at anyone,
while the Messenger of Allah was calling you from behind.
So, Allah repaid you with distress upon distress
as you would not grieve for that which has, had escaped you
or for that which had befallen you.
And Allah is fully acquainted with what you do.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ, also says,
إِنَّ الَّذِينَ تَوَلَّوْا مِنْكُمْ يَوْمَ الْتَقَى الْجَمْعَانِ إِنَّمَا اسْتَزَلَّهُمُ الشَّيْطَانُ
إِنَّمَا اسْتَزَلَّهُمُ الشَّيْطَانُ بِبَعْضِ مَا كَسَبُوا ۖ
وَلَقَدْ عَفَا اللَّهُ عَنْهُمْ ۗ إِنَّ اللَّهَ غَفُورٌ حَلِيمٌ۝
Indeed, those of you, who turned back on the day, two armies met at Uhud(أحَد),
It was Satan who cause them to slip
because some blame they had earned.
But Allah has already forgiven them.
Indeed, Allah is forgiving and forbearing.
So, Allah is saying that what happened to you on Uhud(أحَد) is because of your sins, is because of Shaytan(شيطان).
And we'll get into this when we talk about lessons from the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
Allahعَزّوجَلّ also says,
and By the way, all of these Ayaat(آيات) are from Surat Al-Imran(سورة ألعمران)
قُلْ إِنَّ الْأَمْرَ كُلَّهُ لِلَّهِ
يُخْفُونَ فِي أَنْفُسِهِمْ مَا لَا يُبْدُونَ لَكَ
يَقُولُونَ لَوْ كَانَ لَنَا مِنَ الْأَمْرِ شَيْءٌ مَا قُتِلْنَا هَاهُنَا
قُلْ لَوْ كُنْتُمْ فِي بُيُوتِكُمْ لَبَرَزَ الَّذِينَ كُتِبَ عَلَيْهِمُ الْقَتْلُ إِلَىٰ مَضَاجِعِهِمْ ۖ
وَلِيَبْتَلِيَ اللَّهُ مَا فِي صُدُورِكُمْ وَلِيُمَحِّصَ مَا فِي قُلُوبِكُمْ ۗ
وَاللَّهُ عَلِيمٌ بِذَاتِ الصُّدُورِ۝
Say, indeed the matter belongs completely to Allah
they conceal within themselves, what they do not reveal to you.
They say; If there was anything we could have done in the matter
we would have not been killed right here.
This is what the Munafiqeen(منافقين) were saying.
Say even if you had been inside your houses,
those decreed to be killed, would have come out to their death beds.
It was so that Allah might test, what is in your breasts
and purify what is in your hearts
and Allah is knowing of that within the breasts.
The Munafiqeen(منافقين) were saying,
Why did we get this ourselves into this trouble?
Why are we fighting Jihad(جهاد)?
Why are we doing this?
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ is saying that you weren't killed because you went out to Jihad(جهاد),
you were killed, because that was the Qadar(قدر) of Allah
and if you stayed home you would also be killed.
So, those who blame the death of Muslims on the Mujahideen(مجاهدين)
and, the ones who are fighting for the defense of the Ummah(امة) are wrong
and they are following the footsteps of the Munafiqeen(منافقين).
When it comes to death
It is a decree of Allah عَزّوجَلّ that you would die whenever your time comes.
And it doesn't make a difference, if you go out or stay at home.
You will die when Allah wills you to die.
So, the Battle of Uhud(أحَد) was a test from Allahعَزّوجَلّ for them.
Don't blame Uhud(أحَد) for the deaths of the Muslims.
This session, or the rest of the session will be about Ash-Shahada(ألشهداء).
There were 70 Ash-Shahada(ألشهداء), Shaheeds on the day of Uhud(أحَد).
So, this was one of the standing points of the Battle of Uhud(أحَد) is the story of Shahadah(شهادة).
It was in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد), that 70 Muslims died as Shaheed(شهيد).
It was in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد) that the Ayaat(آيات) of Shahadah(شهادة) were revealed.
And it was in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد) that many of the Ahadees(أحاديث) talking about Ash-Shahada(ألشهداء) were stated.
The Syed(سيد) of the Shahada(ألشهداء) also died in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد)
and that's Hamzah Bin Abdul Muttalib رضي الله عنه
and when we're using the word die and dead here with Shahadah(شهادة),
it is not the right word to use but we're using it
and I hope that you understand the meaning that really Shaheed(شهيد) is not dead according to Qur'an.
But This is the linguistic term that is used to refer to them,
but it's not really accurate
because the Shaheed(شهيد) is alive.
Two of the Tabaeen(تابعين) went to visit Wahshee(وحشي), who was old at that time.
And they wanted to hear from him the story of him, killing Hamzah Bin Abdul Muttalib رضي الله عنه.
Wahshee(وحشي) said, I will tell you this story
I will narrate the story to you as I narrated it to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
He said, Shall I tell it to you, Just as I did to the Messenger of Allah ﷺ, when he asked me about it.
I was a slave of Jubair Bin Mut'em(جبير بن مطعم),
who's uncle was Tu'aimah Bin Udae(طعيمة بن عدي), who was struck down at Badr(بدر).
When Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) went forth to Uhud(أحَد), Jubair(جبير) told me
if you kill Hamza(حمزه), Muhammad(محمد)'s uncle in retaliation for my uncle's death
then he will be a free man.
So, I went out with the Warriors, I was an Abyssinian
and could throw the spear like my countrymen.
He was pretty good at it.
I really missed with it.
When the forces met in battle,
I went forth looking for Hamza(حمزه) to lie, in wait for him.
I found him right amidst affray, like an enormous camel
striking out viciously at our men with his sword.
Nothing would standing him.
I made use of bushes and rocks to get close to him,
but Saba'a Bin Abdul Uzza(سباع بن عبد العزى) got to him before me.
When Hamza(حمزه) saw him, he said, Come over here,
you son of a woman who does circumcisions.
He then struck him a blow so quickly that it appeared to have missed his head.
he then struck him a blow so quickly that appeared to have missed his head.
I mean, the only way he recognized that I didn't miss is that the head flew off.
I aimed my spear carefully, And when sure of it, I herd it at him.
It struck him below his navel, and emerged between his legs.
He tried to move towards me, but was overcome,
I left him with a spear until he died.
Then I went over to him,
Subhan Allah(سبحان الله), I mean he was even terrified of Hamza(حمزه) when the spear has already struck him.
And then I went over to him retrieved my spear
and returned to camp where I stayed,
I had no business with anyone other than him.
I only killed him to gain my freedom.
I didn't join the battle after I killed Hamza(حمزه).
That's it, I went back to base because that's the reason why I came to get my freedom by killing Hamza(حمزه).
Rasool Allah ﷺ heard of the news of the death of his uncle.
And we cannot imagine, how devastating that was to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
I mean, this was his uncle, He loved him so much,
it was one of the sad moments in the life of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And Rasool Ullah asked, he said:
Did anyone see the death spot of my uncle, where is he?
So one of the Sahabah(صحابه) volunteered and he said, I did Rasool Allah.
So, they went together,
and when Rasool Allah ﷺ saw him, he cried and he choked.
And when he saw him, His stomach was opened
and his insides were pulled out.
So, the man who took Rasool Allah ﷺ there, he said: "In the name of Allah, he was mutilated,
meaning is not the state I saw him in, when he was killed.
I mean this mutilation didn't happened to him, when he was killed.
This is something that happened later on.
And this is when, Hind Bint Ut'ba(هند بنت عتبة), the wife of Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) wanted to eat the liver of Hamza(حمزه),
and she ordered that his liver be pulled out.
So, this is the state in which Rasool Allah ﷺ saw his Uncle in.
So, you can only imagine how sad Rasool Allah ﷺ was.
And later on, Wahshee(وحشي) goes on narrating the story,
he said, I went back to Makkah
but then Rasool Allah ﷺ opened Makkah, so I had to leave.
He said, When I reached Makkah and remained, there until the Messenger of Allah conquered Makkah.
I then fled to Taef(طائف) where I stayed.
When the Taef(طائف) delegation left to see Rasool Allah ﷺ and to accept Islam.
I didn't know what to do.
I mean, now Taef(طائف) is going to become Muslim.
Where can I go.
I told people, I'll go to Syria or Yemen or some other country,
I was in the state of indecision and anxiety.
When someone told me Come on now.
I swear, He'll not kill anyone, who has adopted his religion and testified to the truth.
So, the news of the forbearance and the helm(حلم) of Rasool Allah ﷺ was all over, his forgiveness and his mercy.
So, this man is telling Wahshee(وحشي) that if you become Muslim, he's not going to harm you.
When he told me that,
I went to Rasool Allah ﷺ in Madina surprising him by standing before him and speaking testimony of truth.
When he saw me he said, are you Wahshee(وحشي)?
I replied: Yes, O Messenger of Allah.
He then said, sit down and relate to me how you killed Hamza(حمزه).
So, I related it as I did to you both.
When I finished my account.
He said, Wahshee(وحشي) , Can you remove your face from me.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not want to see the face of Wahshee(وحشي) again,
because it will bring back memories of his uncle.
He said, I don't want to see your face again.
Can you keep your face away from me.
Wahshee(وحشي) said: so I used to avoid Rasool Allah ﷺ
wherever he might be, so that he would not see me.
And eventually Allah Almighty and glorious is He, took him to Himself.
Wahshee(وحشي) later on, joined in the army that went to fight with Muselma Al-Kazzab(مسيلمه الكذاب),
The man who claimed to be a prophet.
Wahshee(وحشي) said, I took the spear with which I killed Hamza(حمزه).
And when the forces met, I saw Muselemah(مسيلمه) standing with sword in hand.
So, he was preparing to attack Muselemah(مسيلمه),
he said, While from, on other side, there was another Muslim
trying to attack Muselemah(مسيلمه).
Wahshee(وحشي) with his spear and the other Muslim with his sword.
So, I steadied my spear, until I felt good about it
and then I let it loose on him and he struck him.
While the other Muslim attacked from the other side
and hit Muselemah(مسيلمه) with his sword and killed him.
So, it was Wahshee(وحشي), who struck him first
and then the other Muslim struck him next.
So, Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم), Who is the one, who really killed him.
And who was that other Muslim, It was Abu Dujana رضي الله عنه,
the hero of the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
Wahshee(وحشي) would say,
If it was I who killed him,
then I killed the best of men,
and I also kills the worst of them.
I killed the uncle of Muhammadﷺ and then I also killed Muselma Al-Kazzab(مسيلمه الكذاب).
It is mentioned that Rasool Allah ﷺ told Wahshee(وحشي)
go and fight in the path of Allah, as you fought against the religion of Allah.
And that is how it is, in Islam if you commit a sin
try to erase it by performing a good deed.
إنَّ الْحَسَنَاتِ يُذْهِبْنَ السَّيِّئَاتِ
Good deeds erase the evil ones.
So, whenever you have committed a sin,
try to make up for that sin by doing good deeds, in order to erase it, and to wipe it away.
I mean, Umar Bin Khattab(عمر بن خطاب).
He said about his argument with Rasool Allah ﷺ
and he felt that, that was something wrong to do.
So, he said;
مَا زِلْتُ بَعْدَ ذَالِكْ تَصَدَّقْ وَ أعتق الرَّقَابْ وَاَصُوْمْ فِيْ سَبِيْلِ الله
After that I remained fasting and giving charity
and praying at night to wipe away that sin.
So, this is how, you should approach your sins and this is part of Touba(توبة).
Do good deeds with the intention of erasing your sins.
And this is the month of forgiveness, we don't want to forget to ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to forgive us all.
O Allah عَزّوجَلّ have your mercy on us
and forgive us all in this blessed month.
Rasool Allah ﷺ saw, a woman after the battle was over rushing towards the bodies of the dead.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told Az-Zubair(ألزبير) to go and stop that woman
Az-Zubair(ألزبير) said: I felt that, that woman was my mother Safiyah(صفيه),
Saffiyah Bint Abdul Muttalib(صفيه بنت عبدالمطلب), the aunt of Rasool Allah ﷺ, she was his Aunt.
So, he rushes towards her and he stops her
She pushes him in his chest and said move away
His tooth was broken that day, his face was wounded
and his helmet was crushed onto his head
It was Ibn Qamia(ابن قميه) who shot Rasool Allah ﷺ at the cheek
and it was Ut'ba Ibn Abi Waqas(عتبة بن أبي وقاص), who hit the lip and lower tooth of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Abdul Razzak(عبد الرزاق) says
The Messenger of Allah spoke a curse against Ut'ba Bin Abi Waqas(عتبة بن أبي وقاص) saying
O Allah may change not come to him, so that he does die as an unbeliever
Ibn Kathir(إبن كثير) commented, and no change did come over him
so that he did die as an unbeliever bound for hellfire
So, what was the reaction to this defeat?
Rasool Allah ﷺ as narrated by Anas Ibn Malik رضي الله عنه, he said;
While Rasool Allah ﷺ was wiping the blood off his face
He said, "How could any people prosper,
Who struck their prophet and broke his front teeth
while he call people to Allah.?
How could these people prosper?
How could they succeed?
When they do this to the Prophet who's calling them to Allahعزوجل
Allahعزوجل revealed the Ayaah(آية).
لَيْسَ لَكَ مِنَ الْأَمْرِ شَيْءٌ أَوْ يَتُوبَ عَلَيْهِمْ أَوْ يُعَذِّبَهُمْ فَإِنَّهُمْ ظَالِمُونَ۝
Not for you or Muhammad(محمد) but for Allah is the decision
whether he should cut them down, or forgive them or punish them.
For indeed, they are wrongdoers.
So, Allahعزوجل is saying the fate of these people is not up to you.
It's in the hands of Allahعزوجل
It is up to Allahعزوجل to cut them down or to forgive them or to punish them
They deserve punishment but if Allahعزوجل wants to forgive them
It is up to Him
So, this shows you that even Rasool Allah ﷺ does not control the fate of humanity.
It's all in the hands of Allahعزوجل
Allahعزوجل is the One, who controls who becomes a Muslim and who doesn't
and who should be punished and who shouldn't be punished.
So, if this right wasn't given to Rasool Allah ﷺ
who are we to claim that right.
It's all in the hands of Allahعزوجل.
Some of the Muslims, when they saw the defeat,
and when they heard the rumor that Rasool Allah ﷺ was killed
because this rumor spread like wildfire in the Muslim army that he was killed.
The origin of the rumor was that he was injured.
But you know, in such a state things could get blown out of proportion.
So, the rumor that was going around was that Rasool Allah ﷺ was in fact killed.
So, how did they react to that
Well, some of them said;
We'd better send an envoy to Abdullah Bin Obaey,
and have him get us a truce from Abu Sufiyan
People Muhammad has been killed
Go back home before they get to you and kill you.
Here we have some Muslims, who were defeated
the defeat reached to their hearts
And under the pressure of the moment
They thought that the best course of action was to go to Abdullah Bin Obaey, the Munafiq(منافق)
because he has good relations with Quraish and to ask him to bring a truce
and Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله) Yani(يعني) The Battle of Uhud(أحد) itself may not repeat
but the reaction of the people can repeat in events that are similar.
So, sometimes you find that when Muslims are under pressure and
when they feel that they could be defeated in battle.
You can have some people who would now think
Well, why don't I go to the government's and ask them to help me
or why don't I go to the enemies of Allahعزوجل and let's have a truce with them.
This is a sign of weakness.
But The Muslims who had strong Eeman(ايمان) in their heart.
What was their reaction?
One of Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) said that he passed by one of Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار)
a man who was covered in his own blood, He was soaked in his own blood and he asked him
Are you aware that Muhammad(محمد), has been killed
The Ansaari(أنصاري) responded: If Muhammad has been killed
Then he must have fulfilled his mission.
So fight on for your religion
Let's die as he died fighting for Islam
So, these are Muslims, who cannot be defeated in their hearts,
even if they're defeated on the battleground.
Defeat will never get into their spirit
they will always have commitment and this is what, in Islam is called Thabaat(ثبات), steadfast
Never was such a Muslim, try to negotiate with the enemy of Allahعزوجل
or ask the Munafiqeen(منافقين)
So, we are employees with Allah, we're working for Allahعزوجل
and reward from Allah was our due.
We're doing this and expecting the reward to come from Allahعزوجل.
Some of us passed away or left without enjoying any part of their reward.
Some of us, died before receiving any of their payments from Allah
Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) was one of these.
He was killed at the Battle of Uhud(أحَد), leaving nothing but the cloak.
When we covered his head with it, His feet emerged.
When his feet were covered with it, his head emerged.
And so the Prophet told us cover his head with it
and place Izkhar(إزخر) some plant over his feet.
And then he talks about the current condition, now.
he said, some of us have their fruit already ripened, and they are harvesting them.
Some of us are receiving the payment for their good in Duniya(دنيا)
while some of us are going to receive it in full in Aakhirah(آخرة).
So he's saying that people like Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) who died with nothing, and didn't see the victory of Islam
and see the world opening its gates to us,
they are the ones who will receive their payment in full on the day of judgment from Allah
but people like us are now harvesting some of their fruits in Duniya(دنيا).
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf رضي الله عنه said,
Mus'ab(مصعب) was killed, yet he was better than me.
Let me go back, this is also mentioned in Al-Bukhari(البخاريْ),
Food was brought to Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبد الرحمن ابن عوف)
and Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبد الرحمن ابن عوف) was the millionaire of the Sahabah(صحابه), he was the wealthiest among them.
So they brought him this nice food
and when he saw the food he said,
Mus'ab(مصعب) was killed yet he was better than me.
A cloak was used as his shroud
Hamza(حمزة) was killed, yet he was better than me.
While we have been granted earthly favors.
He then wept until his food was cold.
Rasool Allah ﷺ came and stood over Mus'ab Ibn Umair رضي الله عنه
and he recited the Ayaah(آية)
مِنَ الْمُؤْمِنِينَ رِجَالٌ صَدَقُوا مَا عَاهَدُوا اللَّهَ عَلَيْهِ ۖ
فَمِنْهُمْ مَنْ قَضَىٰ نَحْبَهُ وَمِنْهُمْ مَنْ يَنْتَظِرُ ۖ
Among the believers are men true to what they promised Allah,
among them is he who has fulfilled his vow,
and among them is he, who awaits his chance.
And they did not alter the terms of their commitments by any alteration.
So, this Ayaah(آية) means that we have a covenant with Allah.
Some people fulfilled that vow and they died
and an example of that is Mus'ab Ibn Umair رضي الله عنه.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I bear witness that these are Shuhadah(شهداء)
so come and visit them.
In the name of Who's, my soul is in His hands anyone who gives them Salaam(سلام) up to the Day of Judgment
they would respond back to it.
And this is Hassan(حسن) narration, narrated by Haakim رضي الله عنه.
Sa'ad Ibn Rabiyyah(سعد ابن ربيعة), one of the leaders of Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار),
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to know what happened to him.
So, he said, who will find out for me, what became of Sa'ad Ibn Rabiyyah(سعدبن ربيعة)
whether he is alive or dead?
So, one of the Ansaar(أنْصَار), went looking for him,
and he came and Sa'ad(سعد) was in his last moments.
So, he said that Rasool Allah ﷺ sent me to you to see, how are you?
Are you dead or alive.?
Sa'ad(سعد) said,
Listen carefully to his words, this is one of the leaders of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار)
somebody who's dying, because, of giving refuge to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
He said,
I am among the dead.
Inform the Messenger of Allah of this.
Sa'ad Ibn Rabiyyah(سعد ابن ربيعة) says to you,
May Allah reward you on our account better than He ever rewarded any Prophet, on account of his nation
and greet your people from me and tell them,
Sa'ad Ibn Rabiyyah(سعد ابن ربيعة) says to you
you will find no excuse with Allah, if harm comes to your Prophet
while you still have one eye to blink.
Rasool Allah ﷺ asked this man to go and check out the status of Sa'ad Ibn Rabiyyah(سعد ابن ربيعة)
and Rasool Allah ﷺ told him,
If you find him alive give him my Salaam(سلام).
So, the man comes to Sa'ad(سعد) and said, Rasool Allah ﷺ delivers his Salaam(سلام) to you.
So, Sa'ad is telling to Rasool Allah ﷺ, he is giving Rasool Ullah a message
and he's giving his people a message.
So, these are his last words in Duniyah(دنيا)
He is saying may Allah reward Rasool Allah ﷺ better than he rewarded any other Prophet.
He's saying this before he dies
and he's asking Allah to reward Muhammadﷺ,
even though it was because of Muhammadﷺ that he is now dying.
So, these Muslims of today
who are so stingy and not willing to give up their lives or their wealth for Allahعَزّوجَلّ
and if any harm would come to them
and they think it's because of Islam.
They would be willing to compromise in their religion just to protect their Duniya(دنيا).
Compare that to these Sahabah رضي الله عنهم these Ansaar(انصار)
these Ansaar(انصار), their lives are wrecked, their business is going down,
their farms are not tended to,
their suffering in their families, their children are suffering because of that.
I mean, their entire livelihood is upside down
because of giving refuge to Muhammadﷺ and the Muslims.
And now he's saying: O Allah reward Muhammadﷺ for that
reward him, give him the best reward that You would ever give a Prophet of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
And then he tells his people, who are already dying in the battle, he tells them,
You will find no excuse with Allah, if harm comes to Rasool Allah ﷺ
while you still have one eye to blink.
As long as there is life in you,
you have no excuse if even Rasool Allah ﷺ is pricked with a thorn.
Any pain that Rasool Allah ﷺ feels, while you are still alive, you are to blame.
These are Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار), who gave victory to the religion of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
There upon he died, رضي الله عنه
Abdullah Bin Jahash رضي الله عنه and Sa'ad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعد ابن ابي وقاص),
they met before the battle.
So, Abdullah Bin Jahash(عبدالله بن جحش) said, let's go and make Dua(دعا).
So, they go together, one of them is going to make Dua(دعا) and the other one will say, Ameen(آمين)
Sa'ad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعد ابن ابي وقاص) made his Dua(دعا)
He said: O Allah If I meet the enemy
then enable me to meet a strong fighter.
This is strange, you know, a soldier would usually want to find an easy target somebody weak somebody lame,
Sa'ad says: no, I want to meet a strong fighter, the best of them.
O Allah, If I meet the enemy then enable me to meet a strong fighter
who will fight me and I will fight him
and then give me victory over him
and enable me to kill him and take his Salb(سلب), take his armor.
Abdullah Bin Jahash(عبدالله بن جحش) said, Ameen(آمين)
Sa'ad told him, it's now your turn to make Dua(دعا).
Abdullah Bin Jahash(عبدالله بن جحش) said, O Allah enabled me to meet a strong fighter
who would fight me and I would fight him.
And then he would kill me and cut my nose and ear.
So, when I meet You, You will say
why was your ear and nose cut, O Abdallah(عبدالله).?
I would say for you and your messenger.
And you would say, you are speaking the truth.
Sa'ad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعد ابن ابي وقاص) said: Ameen(آمين)
Sa'ad(سعد) was narrating the story to his son.
And he said, Oh, my son, the Dua(دعا) of AbdAllah(عبدالله) was better than mine.
By the end of the day, I saw his nose and ear tied to a string.
Allah did accept the Dua(دعا) of Abdullah Bin Jahash(عبدالله بن جحش)
and he did meet a strong man, who fought him and killed him
and then, his body was mutilated, and his nose was cut and his ears were cut
and there they were tied in a string
and Sa'ad(سعد) saw that string with his own eyes.
This Dua(دعا) shows that
it is allowed to ask Allah to give you death,
if it is in his path, if it is Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)
Another amazing story of a Shaheed(شهيد) was that of Abdullah Bin Haraam رضي الله عنه,
or actually I mentioned the story of Khaisamah(خيثمة),
and this was narrated by Ibn Al-Qayyim(إبن قيم) in Zaad Al-Ma'ad(زاد المعاد).
Khaisamah(خيثمة) was an old man, but he still wanted to join and fight and we know that old men are excused.
Khaisamah(خيثمة), his son died as a Shaheed(شهيد) on Badr(بدر).
So, he said I missed the Battle of Badr(بدر)
and I was so eager to join,
but me and my son drew lots and he went and was awarded with martyrdom.
So, one of them stayed behind, so they cast lots,
and it came out that Khaisamah(خيثمة) has to stay and his son has to go.
Khaisamah(خيثمة) then said, I saw him last night in my sleep.
He looked great and was enjoying the fruits of Jannah(جنة).
He told me come and be our companion in paradise.
I have found what Allah promise me to be true.
So, O Messenger of Allah,
I swear to Allah, I am so eager to join him in Jannah(جنة)
I am old and my bones are soft.
So, ask Allah, O Messenger of Allah to award me Shahadah(شهادة) and allow me to join Sa'ad(سعد) in Jannah(جنة).
Khaisamah(خيثمة) is saying, I'm getting old,
I'm missing the train, I'm afraid that if I don't die as a Shaheed(شهيد) now
I might end up dying on my bed.
So, O messenger of Allah make Dua(دعا) that I die as a Shaheed(شهيد).
I want to meet my son, I want to join him in Jannah(جنه).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ did make Dua(دعا) for him and he did die as a shaheed رضي الله عنه.
Wahb Al-Muzani(وهب المزني),
these are not from Madina, but they're from outside, from a tribe called Muzaina(مزينه).
He and his relative were shepherds and they came to Madina with their sheep
and they came to find Madina empty.
They said, Where is everyone?
They said they went to fight with Rasool Allah ﷺ at the Battle of Uhud(أحد).
So, they left their sheep and they went to join the battle.
They came while the Muslims were winning, they joined in.
But then when the tides returning
they carried on the fight,
they didn't just join because the Muslims were winning,
they were also fighting with the Muslims, when they were being defeated.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ saw a group approaching them
and he said, Who will take care of this group.
So, Al-Muzzani(المزني) said: I will,
Wahb(وهب) said, I will.
So, he advances and attacks them.
And he pushes them back.
A second group comes in and Rasool Allah ﷺ asks for volunteers
Al-Muzzani(المزني) goes again and volunteers
and he stops them and pushes them back.
The third time, he also stands up so this time, Rasool Allah ﷺ said,
Go and receive the glad tidings of Jannah(جنة)
So, he went into fight, and he was throwing himself in the middle of this group,
and then he would come out and attack again and come out and attack again.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was watching that and he would say, O, Allah: Yarham(يرحم)
O Allah have mercy on him.
Rasool Ullah was making Dua(دعا) for Wahb Al-Muzzani(وهب المزني)
and he continued doing this until these swords shredded him and he was killed.
By the way, when they found his body,
He had 20 injuries all of them were fatal injuries
and Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه said;
that is the best death I could wish for.
That's how I want to die.
Look at those injuries and every one of them is fatal and he was still fighting.
Sa'ad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعد ابن ابي وقاص) after the Battle of Al-Qadisiyya(القادسيه)
was approached by a man from Muzaina(مزينه), his name is Bilal(بلال)
because, one of his relatives didn't get his share of the booty.
So, they went to visit Sa'ad(سعد).
So, Sa'ad(سعد) asked this man he said, Are you a relative of Wahb Al-Muzzani(وهب المزني)?
He said: yes, I'm his nephew.
So, Sa'ad, said, and this is years later, this is 13 years later
Sa'ad(سعد) is still remembering that day.
He said;
On that day, when Rasool Allah ﷺ was asking for volunteers to go and stop this group.
It was your uncle who was attacking them all the time.
The third time, I went to join him
because I wanted to receive the same reward that he would receive
because I heard Rasool Allah ﷺ say, you receive the glad tidings of Jannah.
اَبْشِرْ بِالْجَنَّةْ
So, Sa'ad(سعد) said, I went with him
and he mentioned how brave and courageous
Wahb(وهب) was until, he was killed.
Sa'ad(سعد) said, No state of death would I love to meet Allah with
more than the state of death of that was Al-Muzzani(المزني).
That's the best way to die.
Sa'ad(سعد) said;
When he was killed after the battle was over.
I saw Rasool Allah ﷺ go and stand on top of his grave when they were digging it
and waiting right there, until the burial was over,
even though Rasool Allah ﷺ was exhausted.
Rasool Allah was injured and he was tired and he could barely stand up.
But he nevertheless stood up, on his grave, until he was buried.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said, may Allah be pleased with him
because I am pleased with him.
O Allah, be pleased with him because I am pleased with him.
Amr Bin Jammooh(عمرو بن جموح) another Shaheed(شهيد).
Ibn Is'haaq(ابن اسحاق) narrates;
My father related to me,
he is mentioning this, in the book of Ibn Is'haaq(ابن اسحاق)
My father related to me from elders of Bannu Salamah(بنوسلمه), who said;
Amr Bin Jammooh(عمرو بن جموح), was a man exceedingly lame.
He had four sons who fought battles like lions alongside the Messenger of Allah.
When it came time for the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
They wanted to restrain Amr(عمرو) saying that Allah has excused him.
So, he went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said,
My sons want to restrain me from going to battle with you.
But by Allah, I want to step this lame foot of mine into Paradise.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him it's not obliged to you to fight
because you're lame, Aaraj(اعرج), you don't have to fight.
But then Rasool Allahﷺ told his sons,
it is not your duty to restrain him, if he wants to fight let him go.
Allah might well grant him martyrdom and he did die as a Shaheed(شهيد).
So, we learn from this that even if a person is excused from fighting,
it is allowed for him to fight. If it's not obligatory on him, he can still fight.
We know that the blind man has fought in battles,
we know that lame men have fought in battles,
we know that people who are have other diseases did fight in battle.
So, it's allowed for a person who is excused from fighting to join in and fight.
This also shows you how eager the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم were to die as Shaheeds(شهيد).
We'll stop here and carry on In Sha Allah Ta'ala(ان شاء الله تعالى) tomorrow
with some other stories of Ash-Shuhadaa(الشهدآء)
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
وَالسلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته